Guide to the John Franklin Crowell Records and Papers, 1883 - 1932 and undated UA.03.53.0001
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
John Franklin Crowell records and papers
1883 - 1932 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Crowell, J. Franklin (John Franklin), 1857-1931
UA.03.53.0001
9.5 Linear Feet
John Franklin Crowell was an educator, economist, and journalist. He served as President of Trinity College (Randolph County, and Durham, N.C.) from 1887-1894. The John Franklin Crowell Records and Papers primarily consist of materials concerning Crowell's research interests and publications; his presidency of Trinity College; and his activities after leaving Trinity. The collection includes correspondence, reprints, manuscripts, memoranda, scrapbooks, photographs, printed matter, account books, cash books, and grade books. Materials range in date from 1883 to 1932. English.
9500 Items
Access Restrictions
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
Provenance
The John Franklin Crowell Records and Papers was received by the University Archives as a gift in 1938 (A38-1733) and ca. 1941.
Biographical Note
John Franklin Crowell was born in York, Pennsylvania in 1857, and received his A.B. from Yale University in 1883. After serving as principal of Schuylkill Seminary in Pennsylvania, Crowell returned to Yale to study for one year in the Divinity School and for one year in the Graduate School.
At the age of 29, Crowell became President of Trinity College. He served as President, in Randolph County and in Durham, from 1887-1894. Crowell was instrumental in moving Trinity College to Durham and gaining the support of the Duke family. His vision was for Trinity to become a great university and he traveled across the state to publicize its programs. Crowell gradually upgraded the faculty and improved the educational facilities of the college. He was responsible for modernizing Trinity's curriculum, turning it away from recitation and towards research. Crowell was also interested in athletics and introduced intercollegiate football to the South.
After leaving Trinity, Crowell became head of the Department of Economics and Sociology at Smith College. Crowell received his Ph.D. in economics and sociology from Columbia in 1897. Two areas of interest to him were the plight of the poor in N.Y. tenement houses and the development of the cotton markets. Crowell was an economist and statistician for several years in New York and Washington. From 1906 to 1915, he was an associate editor of the Wall Street Journal, and later became director of the World Market Institute in New York. Crowell retired in 1925, and died in East Orange, New Jersey in 1931.
Collection Overview
The collection includes correspondence, reprints, manuscripts, memoranda, scrapbooks, photographs, printed matter, account books, cash books, and grade books. The correspondence includes letters about the relocation of Trinity from Randolph County to Durham and Crowell's vision for Trinity College. Research and writings include research notes, reprints, manuscripts, photographs, and memorandum books. The memorandum books include notes on a variety of subjects including NY tenements, economic and financial subjects, and personal notes. Scrapbooks include printed matter concerning Trinity College, newspaper clippings on commodity markets, and shipping reports. The printed matter consists of clippings, flyers, newspapers, announcements, and other material pertaining to Crowell's interests. The account books, cash books, and grade books are part of the Trinity College Records, and give details about college life. Major subjects of the collection include Crowell's presidency of Trinity College (Randolph County, and Durham, N. C.); his research interests and publications; and activities after leaving Trinity.
Related Material
Herbert Baxter Adams Papers, 1891-1913 (bulk 1891-1902).
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University.
Board of Trustees Records.
University Archives, Duke University.
[Forms part of:] Duke University President Records.
University Archives, Duke University.
Trinity College (Randolph County, N.C.) Collection, 1836-1990.
University Archives, Duke University.
Scrapbooks; Universities and colleges -- Administration; Tenement houses -- New York (State) -- New York; Cotton trade -- United States; Cotton -- Marketing; Photographs; Account books; Duke University -- History; Duke University. Presidents; Trinity College (Durham, N.C.) -- History; Trinity College (Randolph County, N.C.) -- History; Crowell, J. Franklin (John Franklin), 1857-1931; Crowell, J. Franklin (John Franklin), 1857-1931
- Correspondence, 1883-1923 and undated
  Scope and Contents note
  The correspondence includes letters about the relocation of Trinity from Randolph County to Durham, the building program, means for publicizing the College, increasing the endowment, and related subjects.
  - 1883-1887 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Jan.-May, 1888 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - June-Aug., 1888 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Sept.-Nov., 1888 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Dec. 1888-Jan.1889 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Feb.-March, 1889 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - April-May, 1889 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - June-July, 1889 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Aug.-Oct., 1889 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Nov. 1889-Jan. 1890 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Feb.-March, 1890 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - April 1890 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - May 1890 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - June 1890 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - July 1890 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Aug. 1890 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Sept. 1890 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Oct. 1890 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Nov.-Dec., 1890 1890 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Jan.-Dec., 1891 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Jan.-June, 1892 (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - July-Dec., 1892 (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - Jan.-May, 1893 (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - June-Dec., 1893 (Box 4, Folder 24)
  - 1894 (Box 4, Folder 25)
  - 1894, Letter press book. (Box 4, Folder 26)
  - 1895-1921 (Box 5, Folder 27)
  - 1922-1923 and undated (Box 5, Folder 28)
- Writings and Research, 1887-1923 and undated
  Crowell's writings and research materials include manuscripts of Personal Recollections of Trinity College (1929), Stray Notes of a Traveller (1898), and The Process of Social Development: Theoretical Foundations of Educational Policy from the Standpoint of Sociology (1898). Scrapbooks, 1887-1910, include printed matter concerning Trinity College, when it was located in Randolph County and in Durham; newspaper clippings on commodity markets; shipping reports; and other matter. Memorandum books, 1890-1926 and undated, include an enumeration book and clippings from an 1894 tenement house inquiry made by the New York State Tenement Committee, of which Crowell was a member; notebooks on economic and financial subjects; plus small miscellaneous personal notebooks. The printed matter consists of clippings, flyers, newspapers, announcements, and other material pertaining to Crowell's interests, along with some personal records, including certificates of membership and honoraries.
  - Writings, 1888-1921 and undated
    - Reprints of Addresses and Outlines of Lectures, 1888-1899 and undated (Box 5, Folder 29)
    - Manuscript, Stray Notes of a Traveller, 1898. (Box 5, Folder 30)
    - Manuscript, The Process of Social Development: A Theoretical Foundation of Educational Policy from the Standpoint of Sociology, 1898 (Box 5, Folder 31)
    - Manuscript, Cotton in the World's Market, 1912 (Box 5, Folder 32)
    - Lecture Notes, 1912-1921 and undated (Box 5, Folder 33)
      Includes poem by Crowell, The Little Mountain Rose, 1920
    - Manuscript, Personal Recollections of Trinity College, North Carolina, 1887-1894, 1929 (Box 6, Folder 34-37)
    - Lectures, Manuscripts, and Notes, undated (Box 7, Folder 38-40)
      Includes notes and copies of lectures, divided into three folders, on a wide variety of topics. Titles include The Scientic Problem, The Instruments and Documents of Commerce, Slavery, The Economic Solution to the Social Question, and others.
    - Photographs, 1919-1920 and undated (Box 7, Folder 41)
      Eleven black and white photographs showing several U.S. ports, wharves, and terminals, as well as cargoes of coffee, lumber, and hemp.
  - Memorandum Books, 1890-1926 and undated
    Includes an enumeration book and clippings from an 1894 tenement house inquiry made by the New York State Tenement Committee, of which Crowell was a member, small miscellaneous personal accounts, and notebooks on econocmic and financial subjects.
    - 1890-1891 (Box 7, Folder 42)
    - [1892] (Box 7, Folder 43)
    - Notes and Clippings on N.Y. Tenements, 1894 (Box 8, Folder 44)
    - 2 Books, Economic Subjects, 1898 (Box 8, Folder 45)
    - 1910-1926 (Box 8, Folder 46)
    - 1914-1917 (Box 8, Folder 47)
    - 1915-1917 (Box 8, Folder 48)
    - 1916 (Box 8, Folder 49)
    - 1920 (Box 8, Folder 50)
    - Financial Subjects, undated (Box 8, Folder 51)
  - Scrapbooks, 1887-1910
    The scrapbooks contain materials collected by Crowell on a wide variety of topics. The scrapbooks from 1887-1894, 1890, and 1891-1910 deal with Trinity College, when it was located in Randolph County and in Durham. These scrapbooks contain printed matter produced by or for the college, such as application forms, commencement programs, letterhead, sample forms, notices, and advertising, along with clippings, newspaper articles by Crowell, and other material. The two scrapbooks from 1906-1908 deal, almost exclusively, with the development of agricultural markets within the United States.
    - 1887-1894 (Box 8, Folder 52)
    - 1890 (Box 8, Folder 53)
    - 1891-1910 (Box 8, Folder 54)
    - 1906-1907 (Box 9, Folder 55)
    - 1907-1908 (Box 10, Folder 56)
  - Printed Materials, 1888-1932 and undated
    Includes printed materials collected by Crowell to aid his writings and research, and for personal use.
    - Clippings, bulletins, and souvenirs, 1888-1932 (Box 10, Folder 57)
    - Clippings, 1889-1923 and undated (Box 10, Folder 58)
    - Clippings, 1893-1894 (Box 10, Folder 59)
    - Charts, 1894 and undated (Box 10, Folder 60)
    - Biographical Information, 1901-1905 and undated (Box 10, Folder 61)
      Includes biographical sketch and certificates of membership.
- Trinity College Records, 1886-1923 and undated
  - Administrative Records, [1888]-1894
    Includes petitions from students for holidays and breaks, departmental reports, notes on operating expenses, rules for awarding scholarships, the duty of monitors, room rates, student conduct, and groundskeeping activities, library reports, and athletic reports.
    - Petitions, [1888]-[1890?] (Box 10, Folder 62)
    - Proposals, [1889]-[1891] (Box 10, Folder 63)
      Includes proposals for the creation of a preparatory school (Trinity Park School?), plans for Trinity Law School and a plan for the inauguration of a hospital and medical college at Trinity.
    - Copy of The Doctrines and Discipline of the Methodist Episcopal Church, South, edited by W. P. Harrison, 1890 (Box 11, Folder 64)
      Inscribed with the notation, Presented by T.J. Gattis & Son for insertion in the cornerstone of Trinity College, N.C., Nov. 11, 1890.
    - Library Reports, 1890-1894 (Box 11, Folder 65)
    - Athletics, [1890?]-1892 (Box 11, Folder 66)
    - History of Trinity College, [1890?]-[1893] (Box 11, Folder 67)
      Includes manuscript by W.M. Robbins, Trinity College: Its Antecedents, Its Early Day, Its Founders.
    - Committee Reports, [1890?]-1894 (Box 11, Folder 68)
      Includes reports from the buildings committee, groundskeeping, a discipline committee appointed by the faculty, and others.
    - Departmental Reports, 1891-1893 (Box 11, Folder 69)
      Includes reports from mechanical, school of technology, biology, history, and mathematics.
    - Correspondence, 1891-1894 (Box 11, Folder 70)
  - Financial Records, 1887-1923
    Trinity College financial records consist of volumes and papers. They include bills and receipts, many for the Trinity College Book Room, and five account books, 1886-1890, one of which includes memoranda and minutes of faculty meetings, 1889-1890; the remaining volumes are bookstore cash and day books, 1889-1892.
    - 1887-1888 (Box 11, Folder 71)
    - 1888-1889 (Box 11, Folder 72)
    - 1889 (Box 11, Folder 73)
    - 1890 (Box 12, Folder 74)
    - 1890-1891 (Box 12, Folder 75)
    - 1891 (Box 12, Folder 76)
    - 1891-1892 (Box 12, Folder 77)
    - 1892-1923 (Box 13, Folder 78)
    - Account Books, 1886-1890
      Includes list of receipts and expenditures.
      - 1886 (Box 13, Folder 79)
      - 1887 (Box 13, Folder 80)
      - 1888 (Box 13, Folder 81)
      - 1889-1890 (Box 13, Folder 82)
      - 1889-1890 (Box 13, Folder 83)
        Includes receipts for fees and tuition; expenditures for salaries, repair, equipment, and operating expenses; and minutes of faculty meetings.
    - Cash Books for Trinity Bookstore, 1888-1891 and undated
      Includes four cash books with receipts for purchases made at the bookstore.
      - Sept. 1888-June 1889 (Box 13, Folder 84)
      - Nov. 1889-June 1890 (Box 13)
      - Sept. 1891-July 1892 (Box 13)
      - undated (Box 13)
  - Academic Records, 1887-1894
    The academic records include a volume of prepared examinations for various courses offered between 1889 and 1894; a record of courses (1893); scholarships offered and awarded (1893-1894); roll books for 1891-1894 with lists of matriculants, class and course records; grade books and grade book stubs from 1887-1893; and what may be Trinity College's oldest thesis, Compulsory Education: Why and How? by Gustavus T. Adams (1889)..
    - Degree Applications, 1889 (Box 14, Folder 85)
    - Thesis by Gustavus O. Adams, Compulsory Education: Why and How, 1889 (Box 14, Folder 86)
    - Examination Papers Scrapbook, 1889-1894 (Box 14, Folder 87)
      Includes questions from a wide variety of disciplines, such as physical geography, english history, and algebra.
    - Roll Book, 1892 (Box 14, Folder 88)
    - Absence Record, 1892 (Box 14, Folder 89)
    - Matriculates, Record of Courses, and Scholarships Sept. 1893-June 1894 (Box 14, Folder 90)
    - Student Grades, 1887-1893
      - Grade Books 1887-1891
        Each book is made up of the stubs from the grade books.
        - Freshman Class, 1887 (Box 14, Folder 91)
        - Fall, 1889 (Box 14)
        - [Spring], 1890 (Box 14)
        - Freshman, Sophomore, Junior, Senior Classes, Fall, 1890 (Box 14)
        - Freshman Class, Spring, 1891 (Box 14)
        - Sophomore Class, Spring, 1891 (Box 14)
        - Junior and Senior Classes, Spring, 1891 (Box 14)
      - Grades, 1888-1891 (Box 14, Folder 92)
        Includes weekly and semester grades.
      - Grade Book, [B.B. Nicholson], 1893 (Box 14, Folder 93)
- Oversize Materials
  - Scrapbook that was removed from Box 8, Folder 52. (Box 14, Oversize-folder 15)
  - Scrapbook that was removed from Box 8, Folder 53. (Box 14, Oversize-folder 16)
  - Scrapbook that was removed from Box 8, Folder 54. (Box 14)
  - Examination Papers Scrapbook that was removed from Box 14, Folder 87. (Box 14, Oversize-folder 17)